James Hogg



Mobile: 0450 592 789 Email: james.hogg@hdr.qut.edu.au Date of Birth: 22 April 1996

I am a second year PhD student in the School of Mathematical Sciences at the Queensland University of Technology (QUT) under the supervision of Distinguished Professor Kerrie Mengersen, Dr Susanna Cramb, Professor Peter Baade and Dr Jessica Cameron. My PhD work is funded by the internationally-awarded Australian Cancer Atlas, where my role is to develop Bayesian hierarchical models to generate small area level cancer risk factor estimates. During my first year as a PhD candidate, I have been employed as a tutor for two postgraduate biostatistics courses at the University of Queensland (UQ) and a first-year statistics course at QUT. In addition, I have been a QUT research assistant for a project on the modifiable areal unit problem under the lead of Dr Susanna Cramb and Ass. Prof. Helen Thompson.

Prior to starting my PhD, I completed the Masters in Biostatistics run by the Biostatistics Collaboration of Australia, a program accredited by the Statistical Society of Australia (SSA). In the Masters I obtained the highest level of achievement in all units (GPA 7). My Masters thesis (Grade: 7 (95%)) was completed at the Cancer Council Queensland; I investigated socioeconomic disparities in late-stage breast cancer using Bayesian hierarchical models.

Employment and Experience

February 2022 – June 2022 Tutoring (casual) – Regression Modelling 2 (STAT7619) UQ, Australia

October 2021 – March 2022 Research assistant (part-time) QUT, Australia

September 2021 – November 2021 Tutoring (casual) – Quantitative Skills for Health Scientists (LQB286) QUT, Australia

July 2021 – October 2021 Tutoring (casual) – Categorical Data & Generalised Linear Models (STAT7608) UQ, Australia

Conferences and research presentations

Short presentation Higher Degree Research Academy Event, July 2021 QUT, Australia

Short presentation Bayesian Research & Applications group, August 2021 QUT, Australia

Short presentation Early Careers section of ACEMS Final Retreat, November 2021 Moreton Island, Australia Contributed talk

Title: Searching for stability: Introducing a method of small area estimation for proportions using severely sparse

data

Small Area Estimation, Surveys and Data Science, May 2022

Virtual

Short presentation

Title: Searching for stability in Bayesian small area estimation of proportions

QANZIAM, June 2022

QUT, Australia

Award: Honourable Mention for Best Student Presentation

Poster presentation (accepted)

Title: Introducing a Bayesian two-stage logistic-normal model for small area estimation of proportions

The Bayesian Young Statisticians Meeting, June 2022

Centre de recherches mathématiques at Université de Montréal, Canada

Poster presentation (accepted)

Title: Introducing a Bayesian two-stage logistic-normal model for small area estimation of proportions International Society of Bayesian Analysis World Meeting, June 2022

Hotel Bonaventure, Montreal, Canada

Qualifications

2021 (ongoing)

Doctor of Philosophy (School of Mathematical Sciences)

QUT, Australia

2018-2020

Masters of Biostatistics

UQ, Australia

Dean's Commendation for Academic Excellence (2018 & 2019)

GPA: 7

2015-2017

Bachelor of Music with Distinction: Minor in Statistics

QUT, Australia

Dean's Award for Excellence (all 6 semesters)

GPA: 6.542

Relevant Skills & Professional Activities

Research Thesis (Cancer Council Queensland) – March 2020 to November 2020

Software (in order of proficiency): R, Rmarkdown, Latex, MS Office Suite, Endnote, Stan, WinBUGS, Shiny, JAGS, Github, Julia, Python, Stata

Student member of the Statistical Society of Australia (SSA)

Student member of the International Society of Bayesian Analysis (ISBA)

Attendance at SSA seminars as part of continuing professional development

Member of the ARC Centre of Excellence for Mathematical and Statistical Frontiers, Centre for Data Science, Health Equity Research with Outcomes

Professional Referees

Prof. Peter Baade

Cancer Council Queensland

Senior Manager, Descriptive Epidemiology

Email: PeterBaade@cancerqld.org.au

Phone: +61 7 3634 5317

Dr Jessica Cameron

Cancer Council Queensland

Research Fellow-Spatial Modelling, Descriptive Epidemiology

Email: JessicaCameron@cancerqld.org.au

Phone: +61 7 3634 5387

Dr Michael Waller

School of Public Health, University of Queensland BCA Program Coordinator, Senior Lecturer

Email: m.waller@uq.edu.au Phone: +61 7 3365 5552